what's up ladies of cosmic interest I
have an important video for you today
and it involves training glutes through
pregnancy so there's some gray area here
because doctors are the experts with
pregnancy but not necessarily with
strength training and personal trainers
and strength coaches are the experts in
strength training and they're not
necessarily pregnancy it's what I did
for them to make this video I took four
ladies that were in their third
trimester I brought it into the lab we
did a bunch of exercises and I
interviewed them and the first thing I
want to tell you about training through
pregnancy is that there's a typical
pattern associated with the three
trimesters so it is what to expect
during the first trimester you're tired
you have morning sickness
you know nausea you just don't feel like
training so the first trimester is rough
and then the second trimester that's
your golden window your energy comes
back you have a return to normalcy and
you can kind of resume your normal
training and in the third trimester you
start to slow down it's more day-to-day
and you have more random dates and pains
you have issues with round ligament pain
and sciatica and in general you can't
plan out much because you might have to
work around how you feel but
nevertheless you can and should train
glutes throughout your whole pregnancy
and I'm here to show you how to do it
but the second thing I want to say about
training through pregnancy is that it's
very individual
civic like how to go about it so I
recall trading one client and she she
loved doing front squats she couldn't do
any single again sir says they hurt her
SI joint but she could do plenty of
stuff still and she kept her glutes she
kept her leg mass and kept your glutes
eyes and then you want to do that
because then after pregnancy you're in a
better position to take yourself to a
new personal best and then I've trained
another client do you know love white
stand stuff another during pregnancy who
couldn't tolerate with wide stance one
that loved abduction work another that
didn't like it that much through
pregnancy so it's so specific to the
individual so in this video I'm going to
give you a lot of tips with different
exercise but also just expose you to the
exercise that these four ladies commonly
perform throughout their pregnancy so I
hope it's beneficial to you a couple of
ladies with me this is amber and Vanessa
now amber is 28 weeks and Vanessa's is
34 weeks pregnant so we're gonna show
you first how to hip thrust while you're
pregnant while you're very pregnant
third trimester and also other things
you can do to keep your glutes strong
while pregnant so what are here we're
not using anyway but we've got a hip
circle right above the knee is dropped
and this is an amazing exercise now
amber is pushing out against the bands
as hard as possible on the way up and
down a lot of people only push outwards
on the way
push upwards on the way down and up
going too deep here she's gonna go for
three sets of twenty here feel that blue
and same thing here pushing outwards as
hard as possible all the way up and
Counting not going too deep again three
sets of twenty this will get your glutes
lit up okay so here are some
modifications would maybe you can start
to up
I've got Amber's feet out a little
further than normal so she's not gonna
be perpendicular shins and she has the
bar pushed forward so it's not pushing
up against her lower abdomen and she's
just not going as deep but as you can
see here she's getting a good and range
glute squeeze she's working her glutes
and in range hip extension which is
gonna complement all the flexed hip
extension stuff we do like squats and
lunges and all these things which we'll
go over later so you want to do things
that strengthen the end range so this is
a great candidate here you can still do
Bartlett but just don't go so deep and
amber do you feel a lot of pressure on
the lower abs no not at all if you feel
it in your glutes yes okay so this is
one thing you can do just barbell hit
this just don't go as deep and with the
feet out a little more and then keep the
bar pushed forward a little bit and same
thing with Vanessa here this year out
further not going very deep pushing the
bar forward and you can see her she's 34
weeks pregnant you're not bunching up
against the ball of the belly here it's
not a lot of pressure here so it's fine
she's just do a little pulses it's about
probably like four inch range of motion
but you feel the glutes okay so I've got
Lacey here and Lacey is 37 weeks
pregnant she's ready to burst and here
we're going to show you how to set up
she's gonna come up ought to she climbs
her layup so from here she's gonna kind
of bridge of and then drag your feet
back this way she never put too much
pressure that are on the bump
now she's got the bar pushed forward and
he can see rocks better pushing for it
and she's gonna come down and just dip
the arm not too far come back up so she
- she's doing hip thrust it's just a
shorter range of motion coming out come
up
he's got five reps it's just all the
time she's pushing the bar for little
bit keeping the pressure off of that
region so not too much pressure on the
pump at all it's still fitting the
glutes right good now if you have
accessed an even thinner pad we use
thick bar pads but this is a harbinger
pad it's weight thinner but this lets
her go deeper and without putting the
pressure there so if you do have access
to a smaller pad please use it okay I've
got brandy here with me and she's 28
weeks pregnant now this is her fourth
pregnancy so she's had three kids but
our three previous pregnancies the baby
set up higher in her belly this once
situated low so this is a perfect
opportunity to show that even with a low
pregnancy you can still perform bad hip
trousseau Brandy's going to come up and
you'll see the the path of the band it's
lower than her baby's here she can feel
the head right around here right yeah
she knows the head is right here I think
here's the band placement and she's just
going to pump out some reps now
Deion deep there's not a lot of pressure
on these things
the great exercise for pregnant ladies
if you can figure out how to do the
band's obviously this is a hip thruster
but you can also do it off some power
acts or situate dumbbells or other
things you still have the glutes frog
box some people love them some people
not so much if you don't like the box
you can just do white skins or you know
our stance or narrow stance abducted but
the point is you're always not to be
super heavy you can use lighter load or
even body weight or any bands and
achieve an awesome you're not going too
deep you'll still have some extra love
there naturally so I recommend doing
like three sets of 50 frog pumps so you
have the Smith machine hit thrust and
this is great for pregnant women because
it's very stable and controlled and
again she's keeping the bar out in front
and not going so deep three sets of
twelve is a good starting point for
those sumo Dead's
are a great exercise the wider stance
let's the kind of a belly sink in
between the legs so there's not a lot of
pressure
here's the good morning you can do this
sumo stance or conventional or narrow
stance and just see she's sitting back
and not kind of going so deep
here's goblet squats notice she keeps
the elbows in between the knees or you
can do dumbbell squats double demo
squats like this in the rat position and
notice she doesn't go so deep here so
some women feel comfortable going deeper
than others and here's dumbbell sumo
squats and kind of noticed that in range
glutes squeeze so you don't have to go
so heavy you can get a great glute
workout without using so much weight
here's knee bandit squats you can do
these for high reps
like press is a good alternative you may
or not be able to go that deep but you
know there's nothing wrong with cutting
the range of motion short a little bit
wide stance is good on those here's
curtsy lunges and again you can see
you're not going so deep here you're not
putting a lot of pressure on the belly
next up we have Bulgarian split squats
again the thigh probably gets too
parallel here you're not going rock
bottom knee banded glute bridges
lateral band walks so when people say
you can't train glutes through pregnancy
of course you can do lateral band walks
and things like that unless there's some
crazy complication or something but
ankle weights are great for training
during pregnancy here's kickback
variation and then even if you don't
have any cold weights here you can do
quadruped ed kickbacks you can either do
straight leg or bent leg you just want
to make sure you don't hyperextend the
spine too much
and now the seat
hip abduction machine this is a staple
in in any glute training regimen but
during pregnancy it's well suited
because it's very stable it's not gonna
interfere with the belly
we like three sets of 20 on those or you
could do bands seated hip abduction and
you can do that leaning back upright or
leaning forward and finally here is fire
hydrant which you can do with or without
a band so let's talk about bar placement
during pregnancy so normally you would
have the bar right above the pubic bone
and it's resting on abdominal
musculature right here and hopefully
it's also resting on hip flexor
musculature on the sides that's not what
it's for me I actually used two hip
thrusts without a bar pad and I get a
big bruise here but I've been tolerant
like 600-pound hip thrust but yeah give
me a bruise and once I started using a
thick bar pad I felt more glute
activation because I had no pain but it
wasn't excruciating if your pelvis
happens to be shaped in a way that the
the bar right above your pubic bone is
resting on bone but then it's
excruciatingly painful and even then you
can have a thick bar pad like a squashed
bunch and it still hurts so for those
types of clients which is maybe like one
in six or one of eight female clients I
have to double up on bar padding and use
a sponge and a hampton buck thick
bar pad or something else that I've
Erickson in a spa sponge or something
but I digress for pregnancy you will
actually put the bar on the other side
of the pubic bone so this is not ideal
it's not optimal for a glute activation
because you want something pushing
straight down on the hips and the hip
joint centers are right here so this is
perfect placement but to push the hip
straight down if it's up higher or lower
then it's not an effective load
placement you want it right there at the
hips but if it's a little bit forward
you're still gonna get
glute activation out of it but the
benefit is that your belly will start
here and you won't be in jeopardy
pushing up against the belly so it
protects the belly and the fetus and you
don't have to worry about it being
problematic but you're still going to
get a lot of glute activation especially
if you put the feet out a little bit
further and just don't go quite as deep
you know so the lungs here and you're
just not going as deep and then you're
not going to be push if you were to put
the bar here and go super deep you'd see
that this would be pushing well up into
the lower belly and could be problematic
for the fetus so there you have it I
hope you picked up some new tips and
some good exercise to perform during
pregnancy of course I want to offer this
disclaimer I am NOT a medical doctor I
just have my PhD in sports science and
biomechanics so take that for what it's
worth obviously if you embark on an
exercise regimen run it through your
doctor make sure it's okay and make sure
you don't have any complications there
is a concern about performing supine
exercise but I've looked into it and I'm
not too concerned about doing a set of
hip thrusts for example or set in glute
bridges if it's sustained exercise for
like you know thirty minutes that would
be one thing but I don't feel like you
have to worry according to one study it
did not seem to be problematic so it's
my personal opinion that that doesn't
matter but once again I'm not a doctor I
encourage you to experiment with
different exercises and variations and I
guarantee they're going to
able to find a bunch that work well for
your body and your Anatomy in your
physiology
thank you for watching